<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of two unclean spirits. Or, Two priests by their fruits made manifest to be out of the way of truth, and out of the life of godliness, in the broad way of destruction, therein working deceitfully the works of errour. A warning unto all scattered people that call themselves Protestants and Christians, yet are out of the faith and life of Christ, in vain traditions, and dead forms, wherein the blind-guids are leading them in the pit. Also a declaration of the light of Christ now appearing in every man, even in the conscience, by which all men are left without excuse. With a plain and true direction into the good way, which from everlasting hath been prepared to lead all that abide therein, out of transgression through death into eternal life. A short discovery of the Lords great fury and heavie indignation that will suddenly break forth upon all the disobedient. Written by one, who loves the seed of God, which is unknown to the world, A.H. in the county of Gloucester.</title>
            <title>Discovery of two unclean spirits.</title>
            <author>Holder, Anthony.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E919_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207502</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866547</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866547</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 138:E919[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of two unclean spirits. Or, Two priests by their fruits made manifest to be out of the way of truth, and out of the life of godliness, in the broad way of destruction, therein working deceitfully the works of errour. A warning unto all scattered people that call themselves Protestants and Christians, yet are out of the faith and life of Christ, in vain traditions, and dead forms, wherein the blind-guids are leading them in the pit. Also a declaration of the light of Christ now appearing in every man, even in the conscience, by which all men are left without excuse. With a plain and true direction into the good way, which from everlasting hath been prepared to lead all that abide therein, out of transgression through death into eternal life. A short discovery of the Lords great fury and heavie indignation that will suddenly break forth upon all the disobedient. Written by one, who loves the seed of God, which is unknown to the world, A.H. in the county of Gloucester.</title>
                  <title>Discovery of two unclean spirits.</title>
                  <author>Holder, Anthony.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert at the Black-spread-Eagle at the West-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Anthony Holder.</note>
                  <note>A. H. = Anthony Holder cf. Wing and the Thomason Catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 20:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clergy --  Religious life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168476:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DISCOVERY OF Two unclean Spirits. OR,</head>
            <p>Two <hi>Prieſts</hi> by their Fruits made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to be out of the way of Truth, and out of the life of Godlineſs, in the broad way of Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, therein working deceitfully the Works of Errour.</p>
            <p>A Warning unto all ſcattered people that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Proteſtants and Chriſtians, yet are out of the Faith and Life of Chriſt, in vain Traditions, and dead Forms, wherein the blind-guids are leading them in the Pit.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Declaration of the Light of Chriſt now appearing in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man, even in the Conſcience, by which all men are left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe.</p>
            <p>With a plain and true Direction into the good Way, which from everlaſting hath been prepared, to lead all that abide therein, out of tranſgreſſion through death into eternal life.</p>
            <p>A ſhort Diſcovery of the Lords great Fury and heavie Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that will ſuddenly break forth upon all the diſobedient.</p>
            <p>Written by one, who loves the ſeed of God, which is unknown to the World, <hi>A. H.</hi> in the County of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black-ſpread-Eagle at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168476:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168476:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOVERY OF Two unclean Spirits. OR, Two <hi>Prieſts</hi> by their Fruits made manifeſt to be out of the Way of Truth, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HEnry Hean</hi> of <hi>Ollueſton, William Wilton</hi> of <hi>Elburton,</hi> againſt you two Prieſts, by the Spirit of the living God, I am moved to Declare;</p>
            <p>Hearken O ye Prieſts, this Commandment is againſt you, for ye doth ſhut the Kingdom of Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt men, you your ſelves will not enter, and them that would go in thereat, ye will not ſuffer, for ye have taken away the Key of Knowledge, even the key of <hi>David,</hi> ye have denied Chriſt Jeſus the light of the world, the true
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168476:3"/>light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world, in him was life, and the life was the light of men; but ye have denied the holy one, and the firſt, and have deſired a Murderer to be granted unto you, and ye have crucified the Lord of life, the faithful and true witneſs, who hath loved us, and is waſhing us from all our ſins in his own bloud, whoſe bloud is pretious, and unto us it ſpeaketh better things than that of <hi>Abel,</hi> but the voice thereof cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth againſt you unto the Lord, for verely ye are of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of them that deny Chriſt the true light of the world, the gift and grace of God which bringeth ſalvation unto all them that believe in the light, (I ſay) of that generation will the Lord our God require all the righteous bloud ſhed (in the earth;) And you Prieſts who reject that light of Chriſt, you do diſpite unto the ſpirit of grace, and you trample on the bloud of the Covenant that is our life, which judgeth and condemneth the world; and you who hate the light, is condemned by that light, and from its judgment ye cannot fly, and from the wrath of the lamb ye cannot eſcape, unleſs ye return and kiſs the Son, who is given unto us, the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, who is the way, the ſtrait way to the Father, the way of holineſs, which ye have denied, and now you ſtand in ſlippery places, and your fall is near at hand, for in the broad way you are, in which all did ever periſh that continued therein, it lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to deſtruction, and you are blind and do not ſee it, and you lead the blind into the pit, which devoureth widows houſes, and ye, for a pretence, make long Prayers ſtanding in the chief Seats in the Aſſemblies, and love to ſit in the uppermoſt rooms at Feaſts, and to have greetings in the Markets, and to be called of men Maſter, and you preach for Hire, and divine for Money, and ſeek for your gain from your Quarters, you feed on the fat, and cloath your ſelves with the Fleece, but the ſheep you have not fed. But now the day of reckoning is come, you are weighed and found too light, your ruffe garments are Moth eaten, and your nakedneſs doth appear, for your cozening is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168476:3"/>not by the Spirit of the Lord, and wo unto you who are found in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> running greedily after the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of <hi>Balaam,</hi> who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs, And know this, O Prieſt, who hath violated the Law, and prophaned the holy things, that the Judge of the whol earth will do right, and will not at all acquit the wicked, neither reſpect perſons in judgment, who ſpared not the Angels that ſinned, but caſt them down to hell, and ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the old world, and turned the Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah</hi> into aſhes, making them an example unto thoſe that after ſhould live ungodly.</p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>Henry Hean,</hi> who profeſſeth thy ſelf to be a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, yet are found in the ſteps of them that were deceivers and falſe Prophets, and art in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly life, the hand of the Lord is againſt thee, and thy fellows who are one with thee, in the ſeed of evil doers, out of the godly life, that goeth in the way of <hi>Cain</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, and Serpent-like to deceive the Soul, and ſeduce the innocent who are in the godly life, which was before the world was, before the deceiving Serpent was, and before <hi>Cain</hi> the Murderer was, which life was in due time made manifeſt, to deſtroy him that had the power of death, that is the Devil, which is the foundation, the ground, the root, and original of the ungodly life; and all you that live ungod-like, there is your original foundation, ground and root of bitterneſs, from which the evil branch doth ſpring up, which lives, and grows, and brings forth fruit, in the ungodly life (in the world without God) is the life and breath of all the ſeed of the old Serpent, which is the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed root of the ungodly, which alwayes denyed Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the light of the world, the Son of God, who is the lamb ſlain from the foundation of the world, in the great City which is ſpiritually called <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the ungodly life.</p>
            <p>Yea, which life is condemned, and all that is joyned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, all the wicked and ungod-like are joyned unto it, all proud and luſtful ones are joyned unto it, all covetous and idolatrous ones are joyned unto it, all drunkards and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168476:4"/>gluttenous ones are joyned unto it, even all them that in their eating and drinking doth not ſhew forth the Lords death, but doth feed in their luſts without fear, and are made ſtrong in the ungodly life, from which ariſeth the reprobate mind, and vile affections, being filled with all unrighteouſneſs, fornication, wickedneſs, covetouſneſs, and maliciouſneſs, full of envie, murder, debate, deceit, malignity, whiſpering, backbiting, hating of God, deſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, proud, boaſting, inventing of evil things, theſe ariſe from the ungodly life; and know all ye Prieſts, who are joyned to, and are in the ungodly life, againſt you is the wrath of God revealed from heaven, who bear not the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of him who is created after God, in righteouſneſs and true holineſs, but the image of him you deny who came from the living Father, and hath life in himſelf, whoſe life is the light of men, and as many as believe in the light are in their meaſures raiſed from the dead, and are joyned to the godly life (according to the meaſure of the grace of God, the truth and doctrine of Chriſt, the word in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, by whom the world was made, wherein God is worſhipped) let him that hath an ear hear the truth, where the Devil abode not, the Devil abode not in the truth, he is out of the truth, and hath it not, the lyar and deceiver is out of the truth, and all the wicked who are born of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible ſeed, and walk not in the doctrine of Chriſt, they hath not God, but are out of the truth.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>Henry Hean,</hi> who haſt perſecuted and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned the innocent which hath broken no law, but are in the doctrine of Chriſt, thou art out of the truth, in the ungodly life, joyned to him that abode not in the truth, who art out of the protection of God, and haſt joyned to Petition men to avenge thee againſt the children of God, who ſeek the good of thy ſoul, and are in the godly life, witneſs that of God in thy Conſcience, which hath made thy heart to fail, and thy lips to quiver, its the worm that will never die, and the fire that will never be quenched, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the breath of the Lord, which is the life of the Sons of God, is as a river of brimſtone kindling in the wicked,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168476:4"/>who perſecute the ſeed of God, and make Petitions againſt the innocent, breathing out threatnings againſt the Church, which is in God, the pillar and ground of truth, wherein is the godly life, whom you are found perſecuting of, and when any of the ſervants of the Lord hath from the mouth of the Lord, in love to thy ſoul, warned thee to turn from the evil of thy wayes, perſwading thee to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the light of Chriſt, which convinceth of ſin, and calleth to depart out of the ungodly life, that thou mayeſt be turned from darkneſs to light, from the power of Satan to God, and receive remiſſion of ſins, and an inheritance amongſt them that are ſanctified, and theſe haſt thou ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully entreated, and they have been by thy command caſt forth of thy Steeple-houſe, and by ſome of them thou cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Chriſtians, plucked by the hair, halled forth by the neck, and their mouths ſtopped with their hands, and thy own ſervant abuſing in the ſtreet, and hath given out threatnings againſt them that live in the truth; and thou thy ſelf haſt had others before Magiſtrates who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them to priſon, againſt whom could not be proved the breach of any Law, let that of God in thy Conſcience judge, what image thou doſt now bear, what mark is on thy hand, whether thou art not in the way that Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on went before, where the Dragon, that old Serpent, was head before, and on thy forehead is the mark found by which the Beaſt is known that makes war with the Saints, the ſeed of God, in whom the godly life is perſecuted by the Beaſt, which is out of the godly life: I judge the not, there is one nigh that ſeeth and judgeth, whoſe judgement is juſt, unto him return, that by him thou mayeſt read the number of thy name, which is the number of a man, who is in the ungodly life, unto whom thou art joyned, while thou art an example of pride and haughtineſs of ſpirit, and of covetouſneſs, who haſt filled thy holes with prey, and thy dens with raven, thou art an example of ſtriſe and contention, of malice and revenge, of winebinbing, and of pouring in of ſtrong drink, and of ſuing at the Law, of reſpecting perſons, and of much idleneſs, and thou knoweſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168476:5"/>that thou doſt love the things of this world, which is joyned to another ſeed, which is in the ungodly life, which keepeth not the commands of God, but eateth of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, let that of God in thy Conſcience judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou art not feeding on theſe things Serpent-like, and ſeeketh to intice, perſwade, and draw the ſimple to partake with thee in the tranſgreſſion, that ſo they might never come to know the innocent garment, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to have the pure eye opened, but keep the evil eye open, which cannot ſee God, that ſo the curſe and plague of God might come on them to the utmoſt, even hardneſs of heart, and blindneſs of mind, and ſo be wholly turned away into the earth, where the preſence of God is not ſeen, nor his pure life enjoyed, nor the holy image of God known, and there their nakedneſs doth appear, and ſo the heart luſteth after, and coveteth evil, which is then become the husband, by whom is conceived in the luſt an image like to thy ſelf, whoſe fruits are evil, and ſo thy fruits feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and ſtrengthneth the wicked that is born of the earth, and ſo the bands of iniquity, and chains of darkneſs is by thee dubbled; but aſſuredly the day is come, and coming, wherein the good and bad, the juſt and the unjuſt ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe to judgement, wherefore awake and come forth unto the light from which thou canſt not hide, that thou mayſt receive according to thy deeds done in thy body; and know aſſuredly that the power of the Lord which is now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, is greater and ſtronger than all the powers of the world, and all the plots and policies in the earth cannot deliver thee out of the reach of the hand of the Lord, who is mighty, againſt whom thou doſt rebel, but thou ſhalt not proſper, for his hand takes hold of judgement, the ſword of his mouth is ſharp and keen, and in battel thou canſt not ſtand againſt him, from whom thou haſt had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient warning, but ſtill refuſeth counſel, therefore if thou periſh, deſtruction will be of thy ſelf, and thy bloud be on thy own head.</p>
            <p>And a Warning unto thee, <hi>William Wilton,</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth thy ſelf, to be a Miniſter of the Goſpel, ſent of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168476:5"/>Jeſus Chriſt unto the People at <hi>Elburton,</hi> unto thou I ſay in the name and fear of the Lord, conſider, what Meſſage thou haſt there delivered: Did Jeſus Chriſt ſend thee thither to daub with untempered Morter, to ſew pillows under the peoples arm-holes, to preach Peace to the wicked to whom there is no peace, to ſtrengthen the hands of evil doers, that they may not turn from the evil of their ways, and ſo thou healeſt the hurt of the inhabitants of <hi>Elburton</hi> ſlightly, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Peace, peace,</hi> and ſo cauſe them to truſt in lying words that cannot profit, like unto them that cryed, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord,</hi> and although they ſhould ſteal, murder, and commit adultrey, and ſwear falſly, and burn incenſe unto <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll,</hi> and walk after other gods, they might yet come, and aſſemble together, to whom thou haſt ſpoken ſmooth things, as though they are delivered to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit all theſe abominations? Who ſent thee to ſay the fouleſt ſinner is in the faireſt way for Grace, and ſuch like licentious and unwholſom Doctrines as I have heard thee ſpeak, ſeeing Jeſus Chriſt is the way of Grace, the high way of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the ſtrait, and the narrow way, wherein the unclean cannot walk; therefore thou who art unclean haſt alſo ſaid, that the Gift and Grace of God will not ſatisfie, or, Gifts and Graces out of Chriſt will not ſatisfie, as I have heard thee ſpeak, ſeeing Chriſt is the Gift and Grace of God, and out of him, or beſide him, there is no Grace given, to him is the Promiſe made, in him dwells the fulneſs of the Godhead bodily, and of his fulneſs have all (we) received Grace for grace, which is ſufficient, by which Salvation comes, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, in due time is made, for, and in, all that hunger and thirſt after him; therefore thou that ſaidſt, The Gift and Grace of God will not ſatisfie, art out of the truth, never ſent by Jeſus Chriſt, who haſt preached another Goſpel than what Chriſt himſelf hath Preached, who ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Except their Righteouſneſs exceed the Righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, they ſhould in no wiſe be ſaved;</hi> but thou haſt ſaid, Though we ſin againſt the Lord, and depart from him, yet he loveth us, and accepteth us in Chriſt; let the mouth of the liar be ſtopped: Doth not ſin where it is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168476:6"/>not killed in the fleſh, and taken away by Jeſus Chriſt, yet ſeparate between God and man, in every particular as much as ever it did, and is the curſed ſeed of the Serpent, which is the evil doer, that is born after the fleſh, in whom every man is, whoſe image every man doth bear &amp; in whom every man is loſt, and is without help, or hope, till Chriſt the true light be received, and ſo thereby his Image, who is the image of God, in the particular reſtored, through the death of the mortal birth, or body of ſin; (I ſay) is that ſeed and that nature, wherein ſin lives joyned unto Chriſt, and ſo preſented before God without fault, doth God love the liar, that muſt never enter, or the fearful, and unbelieving, and abomin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and murderers, and whoremongers, and ſorcerers, and idolators, which ſhall have their part in the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone and hath no inheritance in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, and of God, and knoweſt thou not that the wicked ſhall be turned into hell, and all nations that forget God; Chriſt hath no communion with <hi>Belial,</hi> that man of ſin, Chriſt w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll deſtroy, and not ſave, and they that know not the body of ſin in the particular, by the croſs ſlain and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of, they know not Chriſt put on in whom God is well pleaſed, in him is his love placed, and out of him God is not at all pleaſed; and let ſhame cover thy face, who art found a falſe witneſs, that hath brought another Goſpel contrary to the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whoſe light thou art ſeen, and denied, and thy ſpirit judged, who through hypocriſie and deceit, art glorying, ſinging, and boaſting of <hi>Davids</hi> experiences, amongſt a people, before thou or they are come to live <hi>Davids</hi> life, and ſuperſtitiouſly art worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the unknown God, in the idols Temple, whereas the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and true God, dwelleth not in Temples made with hands, nei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her is worſhipped with mens hands, but they that worſhip him, doth worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth, God is worſhipped in the truth, where the Devil is not, the falſe Prophet, the liar, and deceiver, is not; our God is worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the ſpirit of life, in the truth, out of the Idols temple, out of the Synagogues and Steeple houſes which were made with mens hands, even the bloudy hands of the Papiſts, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168476:6"/>are now the idols of the heathen, who deny the light of Chriſt, and therefore know not God, but doth worſhip the Idols, and call them Churches unto this day, but they are dead images, out of the ſpirit, and out of the truth, and they that build them, and they that repairs them, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in them, are like unto them, having ears and hear not, eyes and ſee not, and hearts but doth not underſtand: Ah, fooliſh man, and unwiſe, thy inſcription is to the unknown God, if thou hadſt an eye to ſee thou mightſt read it, how thy worſhips ſtands in thy own will, and thy own time, out of God and his will, and for thy own ends, doſt greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor the living and true God, who is onely known and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed in that truth, and not at all known, nor enjoyed in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>doll, nor found amongſt Idolaters, though they cut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and cry aloud, yet there is no anſwer, let that of God in thy conſcience witneſs, even the light of Chriſt, which light doth condemne thee for taking of tythes, and ſelling of tythes, ſeeing that Chriſt hath changed the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and alſo changed the Law, and is come, the Mediator of a better Covenant, even Chriſt, the ſecond Prieſt, not made by the Law of a carnal Commandment, but by the oath of God, after the power of, an endleſs life, he is the reſurrection and the life, in which the ſecond Prieſthood ſtands which live of the Goſpel, which is the power of God, the power of an endleſs life, if thou haſt an care to hear thou mayſt hear, (I ſay) the power of God, which hath aboliſhed the firſt Prieſthood, which could not continue by reaſon of death, even <hi>Levi</hi> to whom tythes was paid, a figure ſerving for the time then, of Chriſt the ſecond Prieſt, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh came of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> which by the Law, never received tythes, of the tribe of Judah, there is nothing ſpoken of Prieſthood, neither of tythes; — Now thou and all you Prieſts, that by a carnal Commandment, doth take tythes, are not in the power of, an endleſſe life, which is the power of the Goſpel, the ſecond Prieſthood, the wiſdom of God, and power of God, a Croſs to the firſt Prieſthood, to tythes, ſacrifices, and offerings, and all things in the changeable, in that, that cannot continue by reaſon of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168476:7"/>death, is, all that, that is out of the power of an endleſs life, but now the firſt Prieſthood that takes tythes, and all that run for filthy lucre, and preach for hire, and divine for money, are out of the power of an endleſs life, all falſe teachers, liars, and deceivers, that run before they are ſent, that uſe their tongues and ſaith the Lord ſaith, when the Lord never ſpake to them, are in the luſts of covetouſneſs, which is idolatry, and are out of the power of an endleſs life, therefore own ſhame upon thy head, who takes tythes, glebe-lands, and ſuch like gain thou ſeekeſt from thy quarters, for telling of dreams, falſe viſions, and lying divinations of thy own brain, not according to the Oracles of God, therefore thou couldſt not ſay, when in thy Steeple-houſe, before thy Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I asked thee, Whether thou didſt own Jeſus Chriſt, to be thy only teacher, guide, and leader, (I ſay) thou couldſt not ſay he was, but after a little ſpace thou wentſt away, but from the light of Chriſt thou canſt not fly, for there is no darkneſs nor ſhadow of death where the workers of iniquity can hide themſelves, and by the light which thou deſpiſeſt art thou ſeen in the works of iniquity under death, and after the ſhaddow thereof is thy heart and thoughts wandring, and art not at all obedient to be taught, lead, and guided by Jeſus Chriſt, but art an envying as much as in thee lyes to the pure love of God, and Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo art out of the counſel of God, which is known in the light to all them who are in the life, which life condemns the world, and all that which is of the world is with thee, in the ſhadow of death (there is the tranſgreſſor,) therefore own condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the diſobedient, in whom the power of darkneſs rules and guides into error and deceit, rebellion, and diſo bedience againſt the light of Chriſt, and this by the Spirit of the living God is thy ſpirit, words, and ways, ſeen and judged, who are out of the light, and by the light is condemned, even in thy Conſcience, wherein this warning ſhall ſtand to be read of thee in ſecret.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168476:7"/>
               <head>A Warning to all ſcattered People that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Proteſtants and Chriſtians, yet are out of the Faith and life of Chriſt, in vain Traditions, and dead Forms wherein the blind Guids are leading them into the Pit.</head>
               <p>HEar all ye ſcattered People, who are the inhabitants of <hi>Ollveſton, Elburton,</hi> and <hi>Alveſton,</hi> and elſewhere, who call your ſelves Chriſtians, becauſe you think you have been Baptized into the Church of Chriſt, by ſome that ſprinkled your faces with water, and croſs you on the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, and tell you it was in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, which thing they ſay is Baptiſm, and a ſeal of the Covenant, and then after you muſt learn the Engliſh Creed, and ſuch like things, and ſo they tell you, That you are of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Scripture they take to talk on, and one day in ſeven you muſt come into the Steeple-houſe, which they call the Houſe of God, or Church, wherein you muſt hear and believe, without contradiction, that which they in the Week, have gathered out of old Books, which they find written in Hebrew, Greek, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, which they call the Original, and what ſerves their turn out of Engliſh Books and Scriptures they put to it to make up about an hours diſcourſe, with their own imaginations &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they call the Word of God, for which you muſt pay a large ſome of Money or Tythes, or elſe much of their hours Diſcourſe will be in railing againſt you, though by them you have not been profited at all; ſo they Lord over you, and you call them Maſter; and thus you ſpend your time, and old age comes on, and death draws nigh, and you remain as void of true Faith, and as ignorant of Chriſt and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168476:8"/>your own ſalvation, as you were when you were firſt croſt on the fore-heads, and here thouſands die and periſh in their ſins. Therefore now all you, who are yet alive, in your ſins, walking in the vanity of your minds, in the uncircumciſion of the fleſh, and talk of God, and Chriſt in your vain imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, yet know no other Call, to appear before the Lord, than the voice of a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, which men hath hanged up in the head of your Idols houſe, which ſound reacheth but to the earthly image, that deny the Call of Chriſt, and doth not wait for revelation whereas none knows the Father, but the Son, and him to whom the Son reveals him, but you all ſtand without the revelation and knowledge of the true God, in the houſe of imagery, the outward court, the firſt tabernacle, which is not meaſured nor purified, but you are the Gentils that ſtands thereon, not within, the pure meaſure, but are without the holy place, worſhiping every one his image, in the abomination that maketh deſolate, and ſo you know not the way into the holy place, but are without the pure life, allienated in your minds by reaſon of wicked works: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be warned, all you proud and wanton ones, you fooliſh jeſters, &amp; vain talkers, all you covetous, and worldly minded ones, whoſe hearts are departed from the Lord you are but as the ſtubble, you ſcoffing &amp; ſcorning ones, read your figure, in the duſt, all you carnal minded, the beſt of you is but as a bryar, &amp; the moſt righteous is ſharper than a thorney hedge, you grow on the curſed ground, which brings forth bryars and thorns, whoſe end is to be burned, the Light of Iſrael is as a flame, and the Holy One as a fire, which ſhall devour the bryars and thorns in one * day; ſo verily, all you people, every one, unleſs you receive Chriſt the true light, that light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every man that cometh into the world, you are no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, Chriſt is not your head, and you are not his members, and you alſo, ſhall die and periſh in your ſins. [A Warning to you.]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:168476:8"/>
               <head>Alſo a Declaration of the Light of Chriſt now appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and working in every man, even in the Conſcience; by which all men are left without excuſe.</head>
               <p>THere is no other name given under heaven, whereby you may be ſaved, but by Jeſus Chriſt, who is the light of the world, a light ſhining in darkneſs, but the darkneſs comprehends it not, and this is the condemnation of the world, that light is come into the world and men love dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs rather than light, rather than Chriſt, who is ſet for a light to the Gentils, and for ſalvation to the ends of the earth; for God ſo loved the world, that he ſent his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son into the world, that the world through him might be ſaved; he that believeth in him, is not condemned, but he that believeth not, is condemned already, and the wrath of God abideth on him; tribulation and wrath on every ſoul of man that doth evil, he that doth evil hateth the light, the true light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world, is hated by the world, the pearl of great price; which is hid in the field: the field is the World, the World is ſet in mans heart, there is the World of Faith, nigh, even in the heart, this is the ſure word of Propheſie, unto which you would do well, to take heed unto, as unto a light ſhining in a dark place, even in the heart of man, which is in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, turned away from God, who is light, and therefore cannot comprehend the light, the light not ſhining out of darkneſs, but in darkneſs, under the earth, under the world, the day ſtar not riſen, becauſe the light is not loved, the fear of the Lord is not known, and none knows the Son of tighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs riſen in the heart, but thoſe that fear the Lord; and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168476:9"/>all you that know not the fear of the Lord, you are not come to the beginning of wiſdom, and you who are out of the light, doth not know the place of wiſdom, though death and deſtruction may have the ſame, yet it is hid from the eyes of all living, all that live out of the fear of the Lord, yet notwithſtanding unto man God ſaith, <hi>Behold, the fear of the Lord, that is Wiſdom, and to depart from evil, that is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi> Therefore every one, both ſmall and great, to the voyce of Wiſdom hearken, at the poſts of her gates wait, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at the light of Chriſt in the Conſcience, which convinceth you of ſin, and diſcovers to you what is evil, and out of the fear of the Lord, and maketh manifeſt what is good, and therein you will come to know, the fear of the Lord, which is the beginning of wiſdome, and this I declare freely unto you, is the grace of God, which bringeth ſalvation that hath appeared to all men, and it now teacheth, to deny all ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and worldly luſts; and all that believe in it, and are obedient to it, doth receive the living power of God, by which they live righteouſly, ſoberly, and godly, in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world: For of a truth there is no other way by which you can eſcape the wrath of God and eternal deſtruction of your ſouls, but only by receiving and owning the meaſure of light, that comes from Jeſus Chriſt, the eternal Son of God, the Mediator between God and man, and then in the light you will come to know the word of Reconcilliation which none knows tell they receives Chriſt the light of the world, he alone is the Word of God, even the word of Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without which you are all eternally loſt, and are a far off from God, while you are out of Chriſt, and none comes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him but them whom the Father draws, therefore friends every one, while it is called to day, harden not your hearts againſt the drawings of God the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Father of lights, who deſireth not the death of a Sinner, but that you might return and live, if you return, return unto the Lord, which none can come unto, but by Chriſt, who is the way, the truth, and the light, and all that believe not in the light, are out of the way, even the way of the juſt, that leadeth unto life, and they are in the broad way
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168476:9"/>that leadeth to deſtruction, wherein all are that deny the light, and they go aſtray from God in every thought, word, and work; yet in this condition all men are left without excuſe, becauſe that which may be known of God is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in man, even the light of the Son of God, hath ſhe wed it unto man what is good, and what the Lord requires, and giveth ſentence againſt the evil work that is contrary to the pure Law of God; for the work of the Law being written in the heart, the conſcience bearing witneſs, &amp; the thoughts continually accuſeth and condemneth for evil, here you are all left without excuſe, and the Lord will be juſt in your deſtruction, for ignorance none of you can plead, and the eye of God is open, he winketh not, the light is the eye, Chriſt is the light, that is now appearing, in which, if you believe not, you ſhall periſh eternally.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:168476:10"/>
               <head>A Plain and true Direction into the Good Way, which from everlaſting, hath been prepared, to lead all that abide therein, out of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion through Death, into eternal Life.</head>
               <p>NOw every one, to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt turn in your minds, that you may every one in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, come to find the Talant that is hid in the earth, much ſlighted and not eſteemed by you, and wait that you may improve it for advantage, leaſt the Lord come and find you with the wicked and flothful ſervant, and ſo turn you, who hath deſpiſed the meaſure of light, into utter darkneſs, then will you find weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, when the Lord hath taken his own from you, the time of his long ſuffering, and patient forbearance will be over, and then time will be no more, in which you may be ſaved, but with the curſed remain eternally, to be tormented with the Devil and his Angels, then what will the whole world advantage you, when you ſhall feel the wrath of God, even the eternal loſs of your ſouls; therefore be diligent, before it be too late, for the ſpirit will not alwayes ſtrive with man: Now every one, conſider, hath not you had ſomething within you, that when you have told a L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, or been Drunk, or Swear, or Steal, or ſecretly done wrong to your Neighbour, or blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed the Name of Chriſt, or any evil that you have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, have accuſed and condemned you, even in the very conſcience, and then many times ſome of you have reſolved never to do ſo again; but then becauſe ſentence, againſt the evil work hath not been ſpeedily executed, the heart grows
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168476:10"/>hard, and is wholly ſet again to do wickedly, and ſo rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, againſt the light, even the ſpirit of truth, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth the world of ſin, which hath long ſtrived with many of you, and is preſſed under as a Cart is preſt with ſheaves, therefore now let not pride, &amp; hardneſs of heart prevail, but come down, through the Rocks and Mountains, of earth,
<note place="margin">For now you are Children of the Night.</note> and duſt, and ſin, even in the heart, which ſeparates you from the light, even the meaſure of the manifeſtation of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is given to every man, to profit withal, that ſo you may come to ſee the Son, and to enjoy the light thereof, that thereby your feet may be guided into the way of peace, which is the old way, and the good way, wherein peace is found to the ſoul, even to as many as are in the way, and here you will all come to know, what the peace of God is to, and what can never enter into peace, as you own and receive the light of Chriſt, you will ſee in the light, every thing that ſtands out of the light, and that which ſtands out of the light, you will ſee condemned by the light, as your minds is turned out of that which is condemned, into the light which doth condemne, you will ſee the curſed ground from which all evil doth ariſe, and keep you down in death, under the chains of death, and bands of iniquity in the fall from God, ſo you will know the want of life, and your loſt condition you will then come to ſee, how you are without God, and without ſtrength, dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, (and until you ſee this, you are yet loſt) and as your minds is ſtayed in the light, you will ſee what you did when you denied the light, and how you then pierced the Son of God, and daily crucifie him, and trample on his blood, and put him to open ſhame: And hear friends, you muſt all come to know a better day, when once you come to look on him whom you have pierced, when you find the want of life, and ſee him ſlain, which is the Lord of life, you will then mourn over him, as one mourneth for his only Son, and be in bitterneſs as one for his firſt-born, into the valley you muſt all come, and there the Lord will plead with you, and ſorrow and pangs will you then come to ſeel, even as a woman in travel; and as you there wait in the light, you will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168476:11"/>find the light ariſe, and the life moving within, even in the light, by which you will come to ſee, what it was, that pierced Chriſt,
<note place="margin">He that ſlew the juſt, muſt by the juſt be ſlain.</note> that took away the life of the juſt, and ſo the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer and man of ſin, you will come to know, that is turned out from God, and then the flaming Sword you will come to find, which turns every way to keep the way of the tree of Life, and as you abide in the light, you will ſee the way of the tree of Life, to be the ſtrait, and the narrow way, in which the unclean cannot walk, although you will many times find, the unclean will ſeek to enter unto the tree of Life, but ſhall not be able, becauſe of the flaming Sword; then the wicked and unclean ſpirit will ſeek to ariſe above the meek principle, and will be full of wrath and fury a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the way of truth, and tree of life, and within you there will be murmurings, and complainings, and diſputings, and temptations on every ſide will come, and from every thing you ſet your eyes upon, but then take heed, and let not your thoughts go forth from the pure light of Chriſt, but in it keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow, to the foundation, and ſtand ſtill in the light, and receive nothing that ſtands out of the light, above the light, ſo as you abide low, in the pure gift of God, you will feel the power of God, keeping of you in the hour of temptation, that you may not be overcome with evil, but overcome evil with good, and as you abide in the fear of the Lord, you will find the flaming Sword bruiſing in you, the Serpents head, and here you will come to know the croſs of Chriſt, which is the wiſdom of God, and the power of God, that calleth you contrary to the evil motions in the mind, that ariſeth in wra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h ſubtuly from the wicked one, the corrupt ſeed, but the croſs of Chriſt will appear above, and a fooliſh thing, to the wiſdome and prudence of the fleſh, but the wiſdom of the fleſh muſt be denied, and the croſs of Chriſt muſt be taken up, and as you abide in the light, in which the power of God is, even the croſs of Chriſt, the croſs being taken up, it will remain above, above the wiſdom and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the fleſh, and will bring it down to nought, and all the mortal, earthly, ſenſual part, which is of the world, will be under the croſs, and by the power of Chriſt, will be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168476:11"/>mortified, and crucified, as the evil doth ariſe, judgement will paſs againſt it, and by the alone power of the Lord, it will be condemned, and ſubjected, and brought to death, and ſo here you will come truly to read the Law that was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded becauſe of tranſgreſſion, until the ſeed ſhould come; and as you abide in the croſs, the pure principle which was in bondage and captivity, under the oppreſſing nature, will come to be raiſed, and redeemed through judgement upon the tranſgreſſor, that now in you, keeps the ſeed in bondage, then the Goſpel of the peace, and glad tydings of ſalvation, will be then preached to the Elect, the ſeed of God, which the world cannot comprehend, but as you abide in the light, you will come to know the ſeed, wherein is Faith, and through faith an entrance will be known into the eternal reſt where the new Covenant and Promiſes of God is received and known, where all the Children of the Lord are taught of the Lord, and doth know the Lord, from the leaſt to the greateſt of them, and then Chriſt is known and not till then, and then as you abide in the light, you will know a joyning unto Chriſt, the head of the body, which ought not to be covered, and ſo the image and glory of God you will come to ſee; and worſhip in the ſpirit, and in the truth, with whom you will have peace, and acceptance, in the preſence of God, and in the light of God, and in his pure preſence, Chriſt you will come to know to be your only leader and guide, true Prophet and teacher, by whom alone you will ſee the dragon, the beaſt, and the falſe Prophet, that maketh war with the Lamb, and as you abide in the light, you will abide with the Lamb, and then you will be hated, deſpiſed, reviled, ſcoffed at, and ſcorned, perſecuted, and killed all the day long, as we are now, even at thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day, who live god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Chriſt Jeſus, to which, that of God in all conſciences doth bear witneſs, and friends, as you then abide with the Lamb, you will know all them, that are againſt the Lamb, even all that are out of the light, you will ſee againſt the Lamb all greedy doers, all devouring wolves, falſe prophets, deceivers, theeves, robbers, and hirelings, that comes nor in by Chriſt the door of the Sheep-fold, and then the true
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168476:12"/>ſold, you will come to know, as you abide in the light, you abide in the ſold, with the true ſheep and lambs of Chriſt, you will partake of the living food and bread of Life, and then you will know the communion of Saints, and the table of the Lord, by which you will be ſtrengthened, and grow up in Chriſt, the true Vine, to partake of the life and power of holineſs, that thereby you may be, living branches, to bring forth fruits of Righteouſneſs unto God in due ſeaſon, which only is accepted of the Lord; and friends, as you come through theſe things, into Chriſt the living Vine, in the Vine abide, elſe you will become withered branches, that will bring forth no fruit, and then you muſt be again cut off, and caſt into the fire, (and this ſhall be a warning to them, who are in the Vine) and until theſe things be truly witneſſed, and in meaſure paſſed through, you are not at all accepted, though you hear, and read, and ſing, and pray, break bread, and are baptized with water, and give all your goods to the poor, and your bodies to be burned, you are but as tinckling Braſs, and as ſounding Cymbals, while you remain, uncircumciſed in hearts and ears, the Lord hath no pleaſure in you, neither doth he accept a ſacrifice at your hands, it is even, as if you ſlew a man, unleſs you be born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, you can never enter into the Kingdom of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:168476:12"/>
               <head>A Diſcovery of the Lords great Fury and heavie Indignation that will ſuddenly break forth upon all the Diſobedient.</head>
               <p>NOw therefore be ye not mockers, leſt your hands be made ſtrong; for I have heard from the Lord God of Hoſts, a conſumption determined upon the whole earth: This in obedience unto the Lord, and in much love to your Souls, I have given you warning, before it be too late, that you may not be conſumed with the Adulterous and wicked Generation, againſt whom the wrath of the Lord God doth exceedingly burn, and he cannot long hold his hand, for his fury is even ready to break forth as fire, and the flame there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, will burn up all the wicked, and therefore let it not ſeem to you as an idle tale, but remember the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> [<hi>the old World</hi>] and of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> which after ſufficient warning, was by the Lord over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown: Thus I am free of your blood, and my Conſcience is clear of you, in the ſight of God, whether you hear or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Anthony Holder.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:168476:13"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:168476:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
